Register to The Charles Ives Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Charles Ives Papers
1874-1983
MSS 14
Yale University Music Library
51
(70 boxes)
Music, correspondence and other writings, photographs, and additional materials by and about the American composer and insurance executive Charles Ives (1874-1954)
Ives, Charles, 1874-1954
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Some of the materials may be stored at the Library's off-campus shelving facility, so researchers should allow at least two business days to have the appropriate boxes paged.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Charles Ives Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Harmony Twichell Ives in 1955.
Arrangement
In 10 series as follows: I. Music manuscripts. II. Literary writings. III. Correspondence. IV. Scrapbooks. V. Diaries. VI. Photographs. VII. Programs. VIII. Writings about Ives. IX. Ives's collection of music by others. X. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Ives Papers include music, literary writings, correspondence, diaries, scrapbooks, photographs, writings about Ives, Ives's collection of music by others, and various miscellaneous materials. The music manuscripts, which constitute Series I of the Ives Papers, are described in John Kirkpatrick's A Temporary Mimeographed Catalogue of the Music Manuscripts of Charles Ives (1960) and James B. Sinclair's A Descriptive Catalogue of the Music of Charles Ives (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1999). Series II through X are described in the present register.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Edward Ives was born in Danbury, Connecticut on October 20, 1874, the first-born son of Mary Parmelee and George Edward Ives. The influences on him as a young musician were many and varied--European concert music, American nineteenth-century parlor music, ragtime, other vernacular and functional musics, sacred music, and his father's unusual interests in sounds. George Ives, being the town bandmaster and a well-trained musician, was the strongest influence on young Charlie; the father's favorite composers, among them Bach and Stephen Foster, became the son's inheritance. As a teenager, Ives was the youngest organist in the state and an excellent athlete. Charles was a freshman at Yale College when George Ives died in 1894. The Ives family, although an early and prominent one in New England, was unusual in its Emersonian interests and actions; ideas of transcendentalism and self-reliance were part of Ives's background. At Yale, Ives was not a good scholar, but he held the position of organist at Center Church in New Haven for four years, and he was already composing extraordinarily experimental music that he learned to keep away from his professor, Horatio Parker.
Realizing that he would not be able to support himself and a family with the kind of music he wanted to compose, Ives determined to make his living in business. He joined an insurance firm in New York City, met his future partner and lifelong friend, Julian Myrick, and soon applied his inventive mind to improvements and innovations in the business that eventually made him financially secure and had long-range benefits for his company, Mutual of New York, and for the insurance business as a whole. In 1908 Ives married Harmony Twichell, a nurse and daughter of a prominent minister, the Reverend Joseph Twichell, of Hartford. They devoted themselves thereafter to a life that encompassed two careers for Ives--the successful businessman and the iconoclast composer. Unable to have children of their own, the Iveses adopted a daughter, Edith, and the family lived comfortably in New York City and in a country home in West Redding, Connecticut. Along with his father's musical talents, Ives seemed to have inherited George Ives's weak heart, for in 1918 he suffered a serious attack that left him a semi-invalid and sapped his energies; his composing days were virtually over by 1920, and business activities were curtailed, ending with retirement in 1930. He died in New York on May 19, 1954.
Ives was a thinker and an inventor of ideas. He thought about music, about life, about music and life together, about the common man, about religion, about politics--and he invented new ways of expressing his thoughts in his music. Ives also was a writer, not as gifted in his literary efforts as in music, but with a bravura style and spirit that simulated his music writing. Ives's literary endeavors were also concerned with music and society, the dangers of war, the ugliness of politics, and the insurance business. During his healthy and creative years, Ives wrote and composed with passion and conviction. Considering that he worked only on weekends and evenings, Ives produced a substantial body of music and literature. His music is often termed "inclusive," in that he saw no reason to exclude any style so long as it served to express his ideas. The songs alone number over 200 and include a wide range--from traditional parlor songs to the most outrageously innovative experiments. The music manuscripts are in themselves unusual visual artifacts, often extremely complicated and at times indecipherable, a situation that has added to existing editorial and publication problems complicated by Ivesian traits such as multiple choices for performers, unusual instrumentation, multilayering, quarter-tones, etc. The availability of Ives's music today is due largely to the efforts of several younger musicians who "discovered" Ives in the twenties and thirties, among them Henry Cowell, Elliott Carter, Bernard Herrmann, Lehman Engel, Lou Harrison, Jerome Moross, and E. Robert Schmitz. Recognition of Ives came about gradually. Foremost among Ives enthusiasts was pianist John Kirkpatrick, who began to play the "Concord" Sonata in the late twenties, finally giving the first full public hearing of "Concord" in 1939, following ten years of study and practice. This occasion proved to be a turning point in Ives's career. Kirkpatrick's continuing dedication to Ives's music as performer and editor assured further recognition and publication. More recently, the Charles Ives Society has been responsible for guiding and assigning editions and re-editions of the music.
Related Collection
MSS 14 HSR, Charles Ives Rare and Non-Commercial Sound Recordings.
Composers -- Correspondence; Insurance companies -- United States; Insurance -- United States; Music -- United States -- 20th Century; Sonatas (Piano); Songs; Symphonies -- Scores; Albrecht, Otto E. (Otto Edwin), 1899-1984; Ayres, Frederic, 1876-1926; Babitz, Sol; Bales, Richard; Barth, Hans Joachim, 1927-2001; Bauer, Marion, 1882-1955; Bauman, Mordecai; Becker, John J., 1886-1961; Bell, Mary; Bellamann, Henry, 1882-1945; Bennett, Robert Russell, 1894-1981; Berger, Arthur, 1912-2003; Biggs, E. Power (Edward Power), 1906-1977; Boatwright, Helen; Brown, Eddy, 1895-1974; Cadman, Charles Wakefield, 1881-1946; Cage, John, 1912-1992; Campbell-Tipton, Louis, 1877-1921; Carl, William C. (William Crane), 1865-1936; Carter, Elliott, 1908-2012; Casella, Alfredo, 1883-1947; Chase, Gilbert, 1906-1992; Chávez, Carlos, 1899-1978; Coerne, Louis Adolphe, 1870-1922; Cohn, Arthur, 1910-1998; Collins, Anne; Coolidge, Elizabeth Sprague, 1864-1953; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950; Dickinson, Clarence, 1873-1969; Dixon, Dean, 1915-1976; Donovan, Richard, 1891-1970; Downes, Olin, 1886-1955; Eames, Henry Purmort, 1872-1950; Edmunds, John, 1913-1986; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Engel, Lehman, 1910-1982; Ewen, David, 1907-1985; Fairchild, Blair, 1877-1933; Finney, Ross Lee, 1906-1997; Fisher, William Arms, 1861-1948; Flammer, Harold, 1889-1939; Fletcher, Lucille, 1912-2000; Foote, Arthur, 1853-1937; Frankenstein, Alfred V. (Alfred Victor), 1906-1981; Freed, Isadore, 1900-1960; Furness, Clifton Joseph, 1898-1946; Gatti, Guido M. (Guido Maggiorino), 1892-1973; Gericke, Wilhelm, 1845-1925; Gigout, Eugène, 1844-1925; Gilbert, Henry F. B. (Henry Franklin Belknap), 1868-1928; Gilman, Lawrence, 1878-1939; Goetschius, Percy, 1853-1943; Goossens, Eugene, 1893-1962; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996; Gray, Donald; Green, Ray, 1908-1997; Hamilton, Clarence G. (Clarence Grant), 1865-1935; Hanson, Howard, 1896-1981; Harris, Roy, 1898-1979; Harrison, Lou, 1917-2003; Herrmann, Bernard, 1911-1975; Heyman, Katherine Ruth; Holbrooke, Joseph, 1878-1958; Hopekirk, Helen, 1856-1945; Ives, Charles, 1874-1954; Ives, George E. (George Edward), 1845-1894; Ives, Harmony Twichell; Jacobi, Frederick, 1891-1952; Janssen, Werner, 1899-1990; Kauffman, Charles; Kerr, Harrison, 1897-1978; Kirkpatrick, John, 1905-1991; Koussevitzky, Serge, 1874-1951; Krenek, Ernst, 1900-1991; Kriens, Christiaan, 1881-1934; Lang, Margaret Ruthven, 1867-1972; Lieberson, Goddard, 1911-1977; Lockwood, Normand, 1906-2002; Lomax, John A. (John Avery), 1867-1948; Luening, Otto, 1900-1996; Mannes, Clara, 1869-1948; Martens, Frederick Herman, 1874-1932; Masselos, William, 1920-1992; Milhaud, Darius, 1892-1974; Moore, Douglas; Moross, Jerome, 1913-1983; Morris, Harold, 1890-1964; Myrick, Julian S. (Julian Southall), 1880-1969; Newman, William S., 1912-2000; Palmer, Robert, 1915-2010; Pazmor, Radiana; Persichetti, Vincent, 1915-1987; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Pollikoff, Max, 1904-1984; Reszke, Jean de, 1850-1925; Riegger, Wallingford, 1885-1961; Roberts, George; Roldán, Amadeo, 1900-1939; Rosenfeld, Paul, 1890-1946; Roussel, Albert, 1869-1937; Rudhyar, Dane, 1895-1985; Ruggles, Carl, 1876-1971; Saenger, Oscar, 1868-1929; Salzedo, Carlos, 1885-1961; Sanjuán, Pedro, 1886-1976; Schmitz, E. Robert (Elie Robert), 1889-1949; Schuman, William, 1910-1992; Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979; Seeger, Ruth Crawford, 1901-1953; Shaw, Robert, 1916-1999; Siegmeister, Elie, 1909-1991; Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995; Stern, Isaac, 1920-2001; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977; Stone, Kurt; Strang, Gerald, 1908-1983; Stransky, Josef, 1872-1936; Stringham, Edwin John, 1890-1974; Sykes, James, 1908-1985; Szigeti, Joseph, 1892-1973; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Tapper, Thomas, 1864-1958; Thérémin, Léon, 1896-1993; Tweedy, Donald, 1890-1948; Upton, William Treat, 1870-1961; Verplanck, William S.; Weiner, Leó, 1885-1960; Weiss, Adolph, 1891-1971; Whitmer, T. Carl (Thomas Carl), 1873-1959; Winternitz, Emanuel, 1898-; Woodman, R. Huntington (Raymond Huntington), 1861-1943; Yates, Peter, 1909-1976; Samaroff Stokowski, Olga, 1882-1948; Mutual Life Insurance Company of New York; New Music Society of California; Thoreau Society; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1898
- Music Manuscripts, Series I
  General
  The music manuscripts of Charles Ives are described in John Kirkpatrick's A Temporary Mimeographed Catalogue of the Music Manuscripts of Charles Ives (1960) and James B. Sinclair's A Descriptive Catalogue of the Music of Charles Ives (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1999).
- Literary Writings, Series II; 3 boxes
  Ives's writings are divided into the following categories: A. Music B. Politics C. Insurance, Fiction, Autobiography D. Miscellaneous
  Ives himself made no such divisions. These have been made for practical purposes of storage, accessibility and retrieval and should be taken only as general categories. A work might well belong in more than one division. For example, Essays Before a Sonata, appropriately placed with music writings, should not be neglected by those interested in Ives's politics, philosophies and biography.
  For additional information regarding Ives's writings, see also:
  Ives, Charles E. Essays Before a Sonata, The Majority, and Other Writings. Edited by Howard Boatwright. New York: W.W. Norton & Company, Inc., Norton Library, 1970.
  Ives, Charles E. Memos. Edited by John Kirkpatrick. New York: W.W. Norton & Company, Inc., 1972.
  Materials in series II range from drafts and manuscripts toward published works to jottings and scraps of marginalia made on clippings and advertisements.
  When "draft," "sketch," or "manuscript" is used, it is to be assumed without further indication that it is in Ives's hand.
  An asterisk shows an item added after the initial microfilming. The item will be found in the additional microfilm reel rather than in sequence.
  Within the body of the register, titles of published works will not be underlined, italicized, or in quotations unless the meaning is otherwise distorted.
  In all cases when a manuscript or typescript is either a carbon copy or a photoduplication, it is indicated as: (copy)
  - Music, II.A
    Pages with technical information about a specific music work have been placed with the appropriate manuscripts rather than in II.A. For example: a Page on Thoreau is with the song, "Thoreau" in 6B(52), and pages relating to "Concord" are in Box 13 with the "Concord" Sonata manuscripts. In such cases, cross references have been made.
    - Essays Before a Sonata
      - Essays Before a Sonata, first sketch (Box 24A, Folder 1)
      - Emerson, Thoreau, early draft (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Introduction and Prologue, version 1 (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Hawthorne, version 1 (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Hawthorne, notes (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Thoreau, version 1 (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Thoreau, last section (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Epilogue, early draft (Box 24A, Folder 2)
      - Introduction and Prologue, version 2 (Box 24A, Folder 3)
      - Emerson, final ink manuscript (Box 24A, Folder 3)
      - Hawthorne, version 2 (Box 24A, Folder 3)
      - Thoreau, version 2 (Box 24A, Folder 3)
      - Alcotts, ink manuscript (Box 24A, Folder 4)
      - Epilogue, ink manuscript (Box 24A, Folder 4)
      - Epilogue, inserts (4) (Box 24A, Folder 4)
      - to 2nd Edition, insert (Box 24A, Folder 5)
    - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord") (Box 24A, Folder 6)
      Folders 6 and 7 were reorganized by John Kirkpatrick 1980 Jul; therefore, their order differs from that of the microfilm.
      See also:
      I/13
      II.C/26/6,7,8/Memos
      III.B/34/4/Arrow
      III.B/35/11/Schirmer
      III.C/37/1/Miscellaneous Correspondence
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), outline 1 (Box 24A, Folder 6)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), outline 2 (Box 24A, Folder 6)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), draft for 1st typing (Box 24A, Folder 6)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), 1st typing (Box 24A, Folder 6)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), list 1 of stars (Box 24B, Folder 7)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), list 2 of stars (Box 24B, Folder 7)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), addenda toward 2nd typing (Box 24B, Folder 7)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), list of stars "out" (Box 24B, Folder 7)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), 1st copy for 2nd typing (Box 24B, Folder 7)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), 2nd copy for 2nd typing (Box 24B, Folder 7)
      - Second Piano Sonata ("Concord"), 2nd typing (Box 24B, Folder 7)
    - Three Places in New England (Box 24B, Folder 8)
      - Three Places in New England, typescript with additions and corrections by Ives of miscellaneous notes, a description of Putnam's Camp, texts for Housatonic at Stockbridge and St. Gaudens (Box 24B, Folder 8)
      - Three Places in New England, notes by Ives toward Conductor's Note (Box 24B, Folder 8)
      - Three Places in New England, typescript with Ives corrections for Conductor's Note (Box 24B, Folder 8)
      - Three Places in New England, typescript with 2 copies (Box 24B, Folder 8)
      - Three Places in New England, typescript with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 8)
      - Three Places in New England, envelope with Ives memo on outside (Box 24B, Folder 8)
    - Washington's Birthday (Box 24B, Folder 9)
      - Washington's Birthday, autograph page of text (Box 24B, Folder 9)
      - Washington's Birthday, typed page of text (Box 24B, Folder 9)
    - Fourth Violin Sonata (Box 24B, Folder 10)
      - Fourth Violin Sonata, drafts for Postface (Box 24B, Folder 10)
      - Fourth Violin Sonata, typescript for Postface with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 10)
      - Fourth Violin Sonata, typescript for Postface with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 10)
      - Fourth Violin Sonata, final typescript (Box 24B, Folder 10)
      - Fourth Violin Sonata, negative photostat of printed Postface with Harmony Twichell Ives note (Box 24B, Folder 10)
      - Fourth Violin Sonata, 5 pp of miscellaneous memos (Box 24B, Folder 10)
    - 114 Songs (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      See also III.B/35/11/Schirmer
      - 114 Songs, 3 pp of lists (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, prefatory material and notes on individual songs (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, early ink manuscript for Postface (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, final ink draft of Postface (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, typed manuscript (copy) missing page 1 (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, letter to the New York Evening Sun and clipping (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, typed page [Majority?] (Box 24B, Folder 11)
      - 114 Songs, 3 pp miscellaneous notes (Box 24B, Folder 11)
    - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      III.A/29/14/Gunn
      III.A/31/15 and 16/Schmitz
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, outlines for article (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, semi-final draft, pp 1-14, pp 11 and 12 missing (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, final ink manuscript (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, typescript with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, typescript (copy) with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, typescript (copy) pp 1 and 17 missing (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, typescript (copy) p 16 (2) and 17 (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - Some Quarter-Tone Impressions, final typescript (copy) signed by Ives and copy with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 12)
      - 1923 Dec 9, typed letter (copy) to Schmitz with Ives corrections (Box 24B, Folder 12)
    - Fourth Symphony (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      See also III.C/37/1/Miscellaneous Correspondence
      - Fourth Symphony, 7 large folded sheets of notes on verso of printed insurance flyers toward A Conductor's Note (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, 7 pp of notes (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, 4 pp of notes (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, draft typescript with corrections (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, typescript (copy) marked "not corrected" (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, typescript marked "not corrected see copy" (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, typescript (copy) signed Ives pp 8-13 only (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - Fourth Symphony, typescript of footnote with memo (Box 24B, Folder 13)
      - 1929 Jan, 3 copies of printed copy from New Music (Box 24B, Folder 13)
    - War Song March (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      III.A/27/13/Copland
      III.A/29/3,4,5/Engel
      III.B/34/14/League of Composers
      III.B/35/12/Silver Burdett
      - War Song March, 5 copies of Peoples' World Nation distributed with War Song March (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      - War Song March, 4 copies typed from the program notes of the New York Philharmonic (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      - War Song March, typed text with corrections (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      - War Song March, drafts of text by Harmony Twichell Ives and Charles Ives (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      - War Song March, miscellaneous notes (Box 24B, Folder 14)
    - Central Park in the Dark (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      - Central Park in the Dark, photostat with memo [whose?] (Box 24B, Folder 14)
    - The Unanswered Question (Box 24B, Folder 14)
      - The Unanswered Question, photostat with Harmony Twichell Ives memo (Box 24B, Folder 14)
  - Politics, II.B
    See also III.B/35/4/New York Post
    As a rule, correspondence, both general and institutional, is to be found in III.A and III.B; exceptions have been made with letters relating to Ives's proposal toward a 20th Amendment, The Majority, Letter to Roosevelt, and Harding Election. Letters are identified by the institution or government office followed by the name of the individual signer in parenthesis.
    - The Majority
      - Davison, H.P., 1916 Jan 1; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 1)
        with Ives marginalia about "Limited Property Right"
      - The Majority, early incomplete draft and inserts (Box 25A, Folder 1)
      - The Majority, draft insert, not in typed version (Box 25A, Folder 1)
      - The Majority, early "dialogue" version (Box 25A, Folder 1)
      - The Majority, typed excerpts (Box 25A, Folder 1)
      - The Majority, manuscript relating to plan of The Majority [after 1922] (Box 25A, Folder 1)
        pp 8 and 20-40 only
      - The Majority, final ink manuscript (Box 25A, Folder 2)
      - The Majority, final typescript (copy) (Box 25A, Folder 2)
    - 20th Amendment
      - 20th Amendment, first typescript with corrections (Box 25A, Folder 3)
      - 20th Amendment, second typescript marked "uncorrected" (Box 25A, Folder 3)
      - 20th Amendment, third typescript and rejection slip from NY Times (Box 25A, Folder 3)
      - 20th Amendment, with Ives marginalia (Box 25A, Folder 3)
      - 20th Amendment, third typescript, 7 copies (Box 25A, Folder 3)
      - Attorney General, 1920 May 29; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - (Bryan, William J.), 1920 May 30; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - National Life Insurance Co. (Collins, W.R.), 1920 Jun 25; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Herter, Christian, 1920 May 27; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Secretary to Herbert Hoover (Humiston, W.W.), 1923 May 12; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Ives to above, 1923 May 16; typed letter (copy) (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Illinois, Office of Governor, typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Mass. State House (Secretary to the Governor), 1920 May 27; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - New York Evening Post, 1920 Oct 25; typed letter (Box 25A, Folder 4)
        with Ives marginalia
      - New York Herald Tribune (Secretary to the Editor), 1920 Oct 20; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Secretary of the Navy, 1920 Jun 8; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Department of Agriculture (Capper, Arthur), 1920 May 28; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Committee on Mines and Mining (Poindexter, Miles), 1920 May 28; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Taft, William H., 1920 Jun 19; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Ives to above, no date; draft (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Ives to Taft, 1920 Jun 21; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
        with corrections
      - with Ives marginalia to Taft, 1920 Jun 21; typed letter (copy) (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - with corrections by Ives, 1920 Jun 22; 3 copies (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - War Department, 1920 May 27; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - The White House (Secretary to the President), 1920 May 27; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Wilt, I.P., 1920 Oct 11; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Ives to above, 1920 Oct 1; typed letter (copy) (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - Wood, General, 1920 May 30; typed letter signed (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - The World, no date; typed letter (Box 25A, Folder 4)
      - A Suggestion for a 20th Amendment, 4 printed copies (Box 25A, Folder 5)
      - Ives to Roosevelt, 1938 Jan 6; typed letter (copy) (Box 25A, Folder 5)
        in blue folder stapled in with 4 pages enclosure and copy of Amendment